Guide to the Thor Hall Papers, 1961-1972
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Thor Hall papers 1961-1972
University Archives, Duke University
Hall, Thor, 1927-
3 Linear Feet 3000 Items
Thor Hall was Associate Professor of Preaching and Theology in the Duke Divinity School from 1962 until 1972.
The collection contains materials representative of Dr. Hall's work as a teacher and administrator in the Divinity School as well as information on the growth and development of the Divinity School itself. It also includes materials related to Dr. Hall's work outside the Duke community, particularly in the United Methodist Church. Of particular interest are the folders pertaining to his work in the preaching clinic which he directed in 1964 and 1965. The American Association of Theological Schools Report as well as items in the folder "Organization and Structure, 1968-1971" chart the changes in the Divinity School during the turbulent years of academic and political unrest.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advanced notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Thor Hall Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1986.
Biographical Note
Dr. Thor Hall was born and raised in Larvik, Norway and educated there as well as in Sweden, England and the United States. He received an Examen Artium (B.A.) degree from Oslo University, a Diploma of Theology (B.D.) degree from Scandinavian Methodist Seminary (Sweden), and the M.R.E. and Ph.D. degree from Duke University. Following seminary, he studied for a year at the Selly Oak College in Birmingham, England, holding a scholarship from the World Council of Churches. During his graduate work at Duke, he held a Crusade Scholarship from the Methodist Church, a Kearns Fellowship in Religion, the Angier B. Duke Memorial Fellowship and a James B. Duke Fellowship.
Dr. Hall, his wife Gerd, and their son Jan Tore came to America in 1957. During his five years of graduate study, Dr. Hall served one year as pastor of the Ansonville Methodist Church in the Western North Carolina Conference and almost three years as Assistant to the Minister and Interim Minister of the First Presbyterian Church of Durham, North Carolina. He joined the Duke faculty in September 1962, teaching in the areas of systematic theology and preaching. He spent his sabbatical 1968-69 with his family at the University of Lund, Sweden, completing work on a major book on Lundensian theological methodology, entitled A Framework for Faith. Other books by Dr. Hall include A Theology of Christian Devotion and a collection of sermons by Charles P. Bowles entitled The Unfinished Pyramid.
Dr. Hall was Associate Professor of Preaching and Theology in the Duke Divinity School from 1962 until 1972. Currently, Dr. Hall is a Martin Professor Emeritus in the Department of Philosophy and Religion at the University of Tennessee, Chattanooga.
Collection Overview
The materials range in date from 1961-1972 and include correspondence, minutes, reports, brochures, and proposals. Two photographs of students at the Approved Pastors School (circa 1963) were transferred from this collection to the University Archives Photograph Collection.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Hall, Thor, 1927-
Duke University. Divinity School -- Faculty.
Duke University. Divinity School -- History.
United Methodist Church (U.S.)--North Carolina
United Methodist Church (U.S.). North Carolina Conference
United Methodist Church (U.S.). Western North Carolina Conference
Related Material
James T. Cleland papers, 1928-1975
Duke University Archives
Duke University Chapel Sermons, 1954-1987 [sound recording]
Duke University Archives
Biographical Reference Collection, 1972-2004
Duke University Archives
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Biographical Sketch (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Association of Theological Schools Report, 1970 (Folder 2)
  - Approved Pastors School, 1962-1969 (Folder 3)
  - Approved Pastors School, 1970-1972 (Folder 4)
  - Duke Divinity School Bulletin, 1961-1965 (Folder 5)
  - Chapel Worship (including worship service programs), 1969-1972 (Folder 6)
  - Christian Social Concerns, 1969-1970 (Folder 7)
  - Continuing Education, 1966-1967 (Folder 8)
  - Divinity School Review, 1969-1970 (Folder 9)
  - Faculty Retreat, 1965-1969 (Folder 10)
  - Honors, 1969-1970 (Folder 11)
  - Lectures and Public Events, 1968-1971 (Folder 12)
  - Field Education, 1965-1970 (Folder 13)
  - Ministerial and Professional Qualifications, 1964-1965, 1969-1970 (Folder 14)
  - St. Michael's [Dumphries, Scotland] Assistants, 1963-1968 (Folder 15)
  - United Ministry, 1971-1972 (Folder 16)
  - Curricular Matters, 1962-1970 (Folder 17)
  - Faculty Bulletin, 1961-1968 (Folder 18)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes and Reports, 1961-1965 (Folder 19)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes and Reports, 1966-1969 (Folder 20)
  - Fieldwork, Summer Visitation, 1964-1970 (Folder 21)
  - Fieldwork Supervision and Visitation, 1962-1967 (Folder 22)
  - Marshalling Responsibilities, 1969-1970 (Folder 23)
  - Organization and Structure, 1968-1971 (Folder 24)
  - Preaching Clinic, 1962-1971 (Folder 25)
  - Preaching Department Policy Matters, 1962-1971 (Folder 26)
  - Recruitment, 1963-1967 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Self-Study Commission Report, 1970-1971 (Folder 28)
  - Student Affairs, Coordinating Council, 1964-1969 (Folder 29)
  - Student Affairs, Representative Assembly, 1969-1970 (Folder 30)
  - Teaching Materials, Christian Theology (200), undated (Folder 31)
  - Teaching Materials, Junior Seminar, Fall 1969 (Folder 32)
  - Teaching Materials, Junior Seminar, Spring 1970 (Folder 33)
  - Teaching Materials, Preaching, 1966-1970 (Folder 34)
  - Teaching Materials, Preaching Seminar, 1969-1970 (Folder 35)
  - Durham Ministerial Association, Newsletters and Announcements, 1967-1968 (Folder 36)
  - United Methodist Church, Board of Evangelism, 1969-1972 (Folder 37)
  - "Design for Witness," 1971 (Folder 38)
  - "Consultation on Evangelism," [at Duke University], 14-15 March 1972 (Folder 39)
  - Task Force, 1969-1970 (Folder 40)
  - North Carolina Conference, Preaching Clinic, 1964-1970 (Folder 41)
  - Western North Carolina Conference, Preaching Clinic, 1965-1967 (Folder 42)
  - Institute for Homiletical Studies, 1965-1968 (Folder 43)